Howells family. Howells family papers (MS Am 1784-1784.13): Guide.
Howells family papers,
1850-1954 (inclusive).
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
MS Am 1784
MS Am 1784.1
MS Am 1784.2
MS Am 1784.3
MS Am 1784.4
MS Am 1784.5
MS Am 1784.6
MS Am 1784.7
MS Am 1784.8
MS Am 1784.9
MS Am 1784.10
MS Am 1784.11
MS Am 1784.12
MS Am 1784.13
Howells family
52 boxes, 2 volumes, 2 portfolio boxes (26 linear ft.)
Correspondence, compositions, and diaries of American novelist William Dean Howells as well as papers of his wife and children.
The collection of correspondence and manuscripts of William Dean Howells and his family began in 1937 when the Harvard College Library purchased an important group of letters to William Dean Howells from Miss Mildred Howells and her brother Mr. John Mead Howells. The remaining papers have been presented to The Library by Miss Howells and her brother in small lots over the years from 1938 to the present.
In this inventory the distinction between manuscripts acquired by purchase in 1937 and the later gifts has been made clear by cataloguing the two groups separately within each "collection." The accession numbers for the gifts appear with the item. In the cases where interfiling of gift and purchase was deemed appropriate, the old catalogue number "800.20" listed with the item indicates a manuscript acquired by purchase.
*42M-608-612. Gift of Mildred Howells and Richard Howells; received: January, 1943.
*42M-862. Gift of Miss Mildred Howells; received: June 18, 1943.
*43M-565. Gift of Miss Mildred Howells; received: November 19, 1943.
*43M-787-792. Gift of Mildred Howells and John Mead Howells; received: May 29, 1944.
*43M-794-795. Gift of Mildred Howells and John Mead Howells; received: May 29, 1944.
*43M-797-800. Gift of Mildred Howells and John Mead Howells; received: May 29, 1944.
*44M-110-122. Gift of Miss Mildred Howells; received: September 22, 1944.
*44M-225. Gift of R. W. Emerson Memorial Association; received: January 5, 1945.
*44M-254. Gift of Miss Mildred Howells; received: October 28, 1944.
*45M-322. Gift of Dr. Cecil Kent Drinker; received: February 19, 1946.
45M-328-329. Gift of William James; received: April 3, 1946.
*45M-353-355. Gift of M. M. Frechette; received: June 1, 1946.
*45M-502-507. Gift of Mildred Howells and John Howells; received: November 5, 1945.
*45M-509-513. Gift of Mildred Howells and John Howells; received: November 5, 1945.
*45M-516-536. Gift of Mildred Howells and John Howells; received: November 5, 1945.
*45M-539. Gift of W. I. Morse; received: Jone 15, 1946.
*45M-565. Gift of John W. Lowes; received: December, 1945.
*45M-789, *48M-227-230. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: June 22, 1948.
*51M-236. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: May 29, 1952.
*53M-96. Gift of Mildred Howells and John Howells; received: December, 1953.
*54M-328-329. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: 1954.
*54M-528. Gift of David P. Wheatland
*54M-531. Gift of David P. Wheatland
*55M-16. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: August 30, 1955.
*56M-193. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: September 6, 1956.
*57M-24. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: August, 1957.
*58-148. Gift of Elsie T. Friedman; received: January, 1959.
*58M-12-14. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: July 18, 1955.
*58M-16-18. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: July 18, 1955.
*58M-79. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: January 1, 1959.
*59M-1-2. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: July 15, 1959.
*59M-161. Purchased from Hamill and Barker; received: February, 1960.
*59M-257. Gift of Radcliffe College Library; received: June 15, 1960.
*59M-261. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: June, 1960.
*59M-281-284. Gift of Mildred Howells; received: 1959.
There are no restrictions on physical access to this material.
William Dean Howells was a novelist and man of letters, United States consul in Venice (1861-1865), editor of The Atlantic Monthly (1871-1881) and of Cosmopolitan (1891-1892), and a champion of realism in literature.
Organized into the following series:
I. bMS Am 1784-1784.4: William Dean Howells materials
A. bMS Am 1784: Letters to William Dean Howells
1. Letters to William Dean Howells (purchase)
2. Letters to William Dean Howells (gift)
B. bMS Am 1784.1: Letters from William Dean Howells
1. Letters from William Dean Howells (purchase)
2. Letters from William Dean Howells (gift)
C. bMS Am 1784.2: Compositions of William Dean Howell
1. Poetry
2. Prose
D. bMS Am 1784.3: Diaries and other papers
1. Diaries and journals
2. Business and other papers
II. bMS Am 1784.4: Tributes to William Dean Howells on the occasion of his 80th birthday
III. bMS Am 1784.5-1784.6: Elinor Gertrude Mead Howells materials
A. bMS Am 1784.5: Correspondence of Elinor Howells
1. Letters to Elinor Howells (purchase)
2. Letters to Elinor Howells (gift)
3. Letters from Elinor Howells
B. bMS Am 1784.6: Compositions and drawings by Elinor Howells
IV. bMS Am 1784.7: Winifred Howells materials
V. bMS Am 1784.8-1784.10: Mildred Howells materials
A. bMS Am 1784.8: Correspondence of Mildred Howells
1. Letters to Mildred Howells (purchase)
2. Letters to Mildred Howells (gift)
B. bMS Am 1784.9: Letters from Mildred Howells
C. bMS Am 1784.10: Compositions, drawings, and miscellaneous material from the Mildred Howells materials
VI. bMS Am 1784.11: John Mead Howells materials
A. Letters to John Mead Howells (purchase)
B. Letters to John Mead Howells (gift)
C. Letters from John Mead Howells
VII. bMS Am 1784.12: Additional material
A. Other letters (purchase)
B. Other letters (gift)
C. Other compositions
VIII. bMS Am 1784.13: Additional correspondence
In accordance with the donors' wishes, the papers have been divided into five sections: the William Dean Howells materials, the Elinor Gertrude (Mead) Howells materials, the Winifred Howells materials, the Mildred Howells materials and the John Mead Howells materials. The first is the most important, for it contains much important material relating to the literary and social history of America in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, as well as valuable information about William Dean Howells himself. Of the last four groups, the Mildred Howells materials is the largest; much of this correspondence is concerned with granting access to the Howells papers at Harvard and with the publication of Miss Howells' book, Life in Letters of William Dean Howells.
Chiefly correspondence, manuscripts, diaries, journals, and business papers of William Dean Howells; together with smaller collections of correspondence of his wife Elinor Mead Howells, and their children Winifred, Mildred, and John Mead Howells. Includes 15 boxes of letters to William Dean Howells from about 600 correspondents; also contains correspondence from publishers and editors, including Henry Mills Alden of Harper's Monthly, Richard Watson Gilder of Century Magazine, and James R. Osgood. A large group of letters from Lawrence Barrett concerns theatrical productions of Howells's plays. Some correspondence relates to Howells's editorship of The Atlantic Monthly.
Also includes significant groups of letters from literary friends and acquaintances, such as Samuel L. Clemens, John Hay, Henry James, James Russell Lowell, and E. C. Stedman. The bulk of the letters by Howells are to family members, especially his wife, his father William Cooper Howells, his sisters Aurelia and Annie, and his brother Joseph.
Literary manuscripts are chiefly poems, plays, and essays. Diaries and journals cover Howells's early life in Ohio, his period as consul in Venice, and travels to various places from 1864 to 1918.
Business papers include contracts for publications and papers relating to real estate investments. Also contains scrapbooks, photographs, memorabilia, and clippings of articles by and about Howells. A bound volume contains letters and tributes to Howells on his eightieth birthday. Letters to Mildred Howells are chiefly concerned with the preparation and publication of her Life in Letters of W. D. Howells (1928). The Mildred Howells Collection also includes drawings, diaries, and clippings.
- I. bMS Am 1784-1784.4: William Dean Howells collection
  - A. bMS Am 1784: Letters to William Dean Howells
    - 1. Letters to William Dean Howells, purchase
      Letters to William Dean Howells from various correspondents.
      - Adams, Brooks, 1848-1927. 2 letters; 1878-1880., (1)
      - Adams, Charles Francis, 1835-1915. 5 letters; 1875-1880 [n.d.]., (2)
      - Adams, Henry, 1838-1918. 3 letters; 1872-1875., (3)
      - Ade, George, 1866-1944. 3 letters; 1902-1919 [n.d.]., (4)
      - Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873. 1 letter; 1873., (5)
      - Alden, Henry Mills, 1836-1919. 87 letters; 1884-1902., (6)
        No. 61 written by "C.B.H." for H.M. Alden.
      - Aldrich, Lilian (Woodman), d. 1927. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (7)
      - Aldrich, Thomas Bailey, 1836-1907. 24 letters; 1878-1906 [n.d.]., (8)
      - Alexander, Francesca, 1837-1917. 1 letter; 1883., (9)
      - Alexander, Sir George, 1858-1918. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (10)
      - Alger, William Rounseville, 1822-1905. 1 letter; 1903., (11)
      - Allen, Charles E. 2 letters; 1887., (12)
      - Allen, Grant, 1848-1899. 5 letters; 1891 [n.d.]., (13)
      - Allen, James Lane, 1849-1925. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (14)
      - Alma-Tadema, Laura Theresa, lady, d. 1909. 1 letter; 1882., (15)
      - Alma-Tadema, Sir Lawrence, 1836-1912. 5 letters; 1882-1883., (16)
        No. 5 also signed by Sir Edmund Gosse,; Laura Alma-Tadema,; Anna Alma-Tadema,; Ellen (Epps) Gosse,; Enis Williams.
      - Alvarar, M. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (17)
        Signed by Alvarar and others.
      - The American Hebrew. 1 letter; 1885., (18)
      - Anderson, Charles, 1814-1895. 1 letter; 1892., (19)
        Anstey, F., pseud. See Guthrie, Thomas Anstey, 1856-1934.
      - Anthony, Andrew Varick Stout, 1835-1906. 6 letters; 1885-1898., (20)
        Nos. 2-6 signed "Harper and Bros."
      - Appleton, Thomas Gold, 1812-1884. 1 letter; 1880., (21)
      - Appleton, William Worthen. 4 letters; 1892-1894., (22)
      - Archer, William, 1856-1924. 3 letters; 1890-1904 [n.d.]., (23)
      - Armfield, Constance (Smedley). 1 letter; 1912., (24)
      - Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (25)
      - Astor, William Waldorf Astor, 1st viscount, 1848-1919. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (26)
      - Aveling, Eleanor (Marx) 1856-1898. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (27)
      - Babb, Edmund. 1 letter; 1857., (28)
      - Baker, William Morrant, 1839-1896. 1 letter; 1873., (29)
      - Baldwin, Simeon Eben, 1840-1927. 1 letter; 1881., (30)
      - Balestier, Wolcott, 1861-1891. 9 letters; 1890-1891., (31)
      - Bancroft, George, 1800-1891. 1 letter; 1875., (32)
      - Bangs, John Kendrick, 1862-1922. 1 letter; 1895., (33)
      - Barrett, Lawrence, 1838-1891. 104 letters; 1875-1890 [n.d.]., (34)
        No. 104 is a statement of royalties for A counterfeit presentment and [Yorick's love].
        See also Wilmon Blackmar to William Dean Howells.
      - Barrett, Wilson, 1848-1904. 4 letters; 1886., (35)
      - Barrie, Sir James Matthew, bart., 1860-1937. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (36)
      - Barry, William, 1849-1930. 1 letter; 1893., (37)
      - Bass, Alden. 2 letters; 1902., (38)
      - Bass, G.E. 1 letter; 1903., (39)
      - Bates, Arlo, 1850-1918. 2 letters; 1883., (40)
        With typed copies.
        TS: *59M-161
      - Bauermfeim, Vincenzo de. 1 letter; 1864., (41)
      - Bell, Helen Olcott (Choate) 1830-1918. 2 letters; [n.d.]., (42)
      - Bellamy, Edward, 1850-1898. 13 letters; 1881-1893 [n.d.]., (43)
      - Bellew, F.H.Temple. 2 letters; 1881., (44)
      - Bennett, Arnold, 1867-1931. 3 letters; 1911., (45)
      - Bishop, William Henry, 1847-1928. 13 letters; 1877-1904., (46)
      - Bjørnson, Bjørnstjerne, 1832-1910. 5 letters; 1880-1884 [n.d.]., (47)
      - Black, Alexander, 1859-1940. 1 letter; [1919]., (48)
      - Black, William P. 1 letter; 1888., (49)
      - Blackmar, Wilmon W. 1 letter; 1891., (50)
      - Blake, James Vila, 1842-1925. 1 letter; 1887., (51)
      - Blinn, Henry C. 1 letter; 1880., (52)
      - Bok, Edward William, 1863-1930. 8 letters; 1891-1894., (53)
        No. 7 with two typed copies.
      - Booth, Edwin, 1833-1893. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (54)
      - Boucicault, Dion, 1820-1890. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (55)
      - Boughton, George Henry, 1833-1905. 1 letter; 1883., (56)
      - Boyesen, Hjalmar Hjorth, 1848-1895. 14 letters; 1872-1891., (57)
      - Brewer, Abraham Titus, 1841-1933. 1 letter; 1879., (57a)
      - Brieux, Eugène, 1858-1932. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (58)
      - Bromley, Theodore T. 1 letter; 1879., (59)
      - Brooks, Phillips, bp., 1835-1893. 1 letter; 1880., (60)
      - Brown, Curtis, 1866-1945. 7 letters; 1916-1917., (61)
        No. 4 with a contract between William Dean Howells and Louis Conard, signed by Louis Conard.
      - Brown, John, Jr. 1 letter; 1874., (62)
      - Browne, Charles Farrar, 1834-1867. 1 letter; 1866., (63)
      - Browne, Francis Fisher, 1843-1913. 2 letters; 1887., (64)
      - Browne, Katharine. 1 letter; [1883]., (65)
        With typed copy.
        TS: *55M-16
      - Browne, Waldo Ralph, 1876-1954. 2 letters; 1916., (66)
      - Brunetta, Eugenio. 4 letters; 1865-1883., (67)
      - Brush, George de Forest, 1855-1941. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (68)
      - Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878. 3 letters; 1871-1874., (69)
      - Bryce, James Bryce, viscount, 1838-1922. 4 letters; 1904-1912 [n.d.]., (70)
      - Buck, Dudley, 1839-1909. 1 letter; 1876., (71)
      - Buel, Clarence Clough, 1850-1933. 2 letters; 1885-1896., (72)
      - Bullard, William Norton, 1853-1931. 1 letter; 1884., (73)
      - Bumstead, S.J. 1 letter; 1887., (74)
      - Burlingame, Edward Livermore, 1848-1922. 4 letters; 1894-1895., (75)
      - Burnett, Mabel (Lowell), b. 1847. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (76)
      - Burritt, Elihu, 1810-1879. 2 letters; 1875-1878., (77)
      - Burroughs, John, 1837-1921. 2 letters; 1894., (78)
      - Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925. 15 letters; 1881-1919., (79)
      - Campbell, (Mrs.) Patrick, 1865-1940. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (80)
      - Carleton, Will, 1845-1912. 1 letter; 1871., (81)
      - Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (82)
      - Carr, Joseph William Comyns, 1849-1916. 1 letter; 1883., (83)
      - Carter, Isabella E. 2 letters; 1867 [n.d.]., (84)
      - Castle, Agnes Egerton. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (85)
      - Cawein, Madison, 1865-1914. 6 letters; [1888]-1905., (86)
      - Chase, Salmon Portland, 1808-1873. 2 letters; 1863., (87)
      - Chase, William Merritt, 1849-1916. 1 letter; 1871., (88)
      - Chesebro', Caroline, 1825-1873. 1 letter; 1866., (89)
      - Child, Francis James, 1825-1896. 8 letters; 1887 [n.d.]., (90)
        No. 8 with typed copy.
      - Child, Lydia Maria (Francis), 1802-1880. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (91)
      - Cholmondeley, Mary, 1859-1925. 1 letter; 1904., (92)
      - Churchill, Winston, 1871-1947. 1 letter; 1912., (93)
      - Clark, J.S. 1 letter; 1861., (94)
      - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. 1 letter; 1876., (95)
      - Clay, Cassius Marcellus, 1810-1903. 3 letters; 1886-1887., (96)
      - Clemens, Clara. 1 letter; 1917., (97)
      - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910. 225 letters; 1872-1909 [n.d.]., (98)
        Published in Henry Smith Nash and William M. Gibson, Mark Twain-Howells letters.
        No. 16 with letter from Joseph Hopkins Twichell to S.L. Clemens.
        Nos. 19, 26, 104, 142 are incomplete.
        No. 40 consists of 2 leaves, first dated 14 June 187 in SLC's hand and is correct; the second leaf begins "P.S. - 2 days later, being July 6", belongs with a letter whose initial leaf is held at Berg Collection, NYPL.
        Envelope with No. 45 may belong to letter No. 61.
        Nos. 46, 118, 127, 164 are transcripts; location of originals unknown.
        Nos. 95 and 140 are transcripts; originals in University of California Library, Berkeley.
        Nos. 107, 114, 124, 132, 135, 138, 161, 170-173 are transcripts; originals in Berg Collection, New York Public Library.
        Nos. 185 and 221 are incomplete; the other portions of these letters are in the Berg collection.
        No. 64 with a letter from Olivia Clemens to W.D. Howells.
        No. 65 with a letter from John T. Lewis to S.L. Clemens.
        No. 79 with a letter From S.L. Clemens to an unknown correspondent.
        No. 98 with a letter from W.D. Howells to William Cooper Howells.
        No. 101 with portion of a note by Olivia Clemens; with a complete transcript.
        No. 113 with a sketch which Clemens used in his story "The Death Disk."
      - Clement, Edward Henry, 1843-1920. 1 letter; 1887., (99)
      - Clodd, D.W. 1 letter; 1904., (100)
        With a letter from T[homas] H[ardy] to D.W. Clodd.
      - Collyer, Robert, 1823-1912. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (101)
      - Comly, James M. 2 letters; 1863-1874., (102)
      - Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907. 13 letters; [1864]-1890 [n.d.]., (103)
        No. 1 with a note from Ellen Davis Conway to W.D. Howells.
      - Cooke, Henry David, 1825-1881. 1 letter; 1861., (104)
      - Cooke, John Esten, 1830-1886. 1 letter; 1884., (105)
      - Cooke, Rose (Terry) 1827-1892. 5 letters; 1876-1884., (106)
      - Coolbrith, Ina Donna, 1842-1928. 1 letter; 1919., (107)
      - Cotes, Sara Jeannette (Duncan) 1862-1922. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (108)
      - [Cranch, Christopher Pearse], 1813-1892. 1 letter; 1866., (109)
      - Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900. 6 letters; 1893 [n.d.]., (110)
      - Crane, William H., 1845-1928. 1 letter; 1898., (111)
      - Croker, Bithia Mary (Sheppard) d. 1920. 4 letters; [n.d.]., (112)
      - Crosby, Edward Harold. 1 letter; 1895., (113)
      - Crowninshield, Frederic, 1856-1918. 1 letter; 1909., (114)
      - Curtis, George William, 1824-1892. 18 letters; 1867-1892., (115)
        Dall'Ongaro, Francesco. See Ongaro, Francesco dall', 1808-1873.
      - Daly, Augustin, 1838-1899. 2 letters; 1884-1893., (116)
      - Dana, Charles Anderson, 1819-1897. 15 letters; 1884-1896., (117)
      - Dana, Richard Henry, 1815-1882. 1 letter; 1875., (118)
      - Da Ru, Giuseppe. 2 letters; 1864., (119)
      - Davies, Horace. 1 letter; 1905., (120)
      - Davis, Richard Harding, 1864-1916. 4 letters; 1904 [n.d.]., (121)
      - De Forest, John William, 1826-1906. 13 letters; 1868-1890., (122)
        With copy of a letter from Isaac Taylor to John William De Forest.
      - Deland, Margaret Wade (Campbell), 1857-1944. 2 letters; 1896 [n.d.]., (123)
        No. 2 incomplete.
      - Deutsch, Carolyn. 1 letter; 1902., (124)
      - De Vere, Aubrey, 1814-1902. 3 letters; 1870-1874., (125)
      - Dexter, George, 1838-1883. 1 letter; 1871., (126)
      - Dobbin, George W. 1 letter; 1883., (127)
      - Dobson, Austin, 1840-1921. 1 letter; 1911., (128)
        With poem "To time, the tyrant".
      - Dodge, Mary (Mapes), 1838-1905. 5 letters; 1877-1888., (129)
        No. 3 with two typed copies.
        No. 1 in another hand.
      - Doubleday, Frank Nelson, 1862-1934. 1 letter; 1899., (130)
        Signed by another hand.
      - Douglas, David, 1823-1916. 16 letters; 1883-1910., (131)
        No. 10 in hand of W. Douglas.
      - Du Maurier, George, 1834-1896. 1 letter; 1894., (132)
      - Dunbar, Paul Laurence, 1872-1906. 5 letters; 1896-1899., (133)
      - Duneka, Frederick A. 20 letters; 1910-1918., (134)
      - Dunne, Finley Peter, 1867-1936. 1 letter; 1902., (135)
      - Durand, Alice Marie Céleste (Fleury) 1842-1902. 1 letter; 1886., (136)
      - Durand, John, 1822-1908. 2 letters; 1885-1888., (137)
      - Eggleston, Edward, 1837-1902. 4 letters; 1872-1895., (138)
      - Eggleston, George Cary, 1839-1911. 1 letter; 1873., (139)
      - Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926. 5 letters; 1869-1871., (140)
      - Elliott, Byron Kosciusko, 1835-1913. 1 letter; 1890., (141)
      - Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882. 4 letters; 1874-1878., (142)
        Publ. in Ralph L. Rusk, ed., The letters of Ralph Waldon Emerson.
      - English, Thomas Dunn, 1819-1902. 2 letters; 1871-1874., (143)
      - Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901. 2 letters; 1874-1879., (144)
      - Eversley, George Shaw-Lefevre, 1st baron, 1831-1928. 1 letter; 1910., (145)
      - Fawcett, Edgar, 1847-1904. 5 letters; [n.d.]., (146)
      - Ferrero, Guglielmo, 1871-1942. 1 letter; 1908., (147)
      - Field, Eugene, 1850-1895. 1 letter; 1891., (148)
      - Field, John W. 1 letter; 1867., (148a)
      - Fields, Annie (Adams), 1834-1915. 2 letters; 1867-1872., (149)
      - Fields, James Thomas, 1816-1881. 7 letters; 1861-1880., (150)
        No. 4 in the hand of Annie (Adams) Fields.
      - Fields, Kate. 1 letter; 1870., (151)
      - Fiske, John, 1842-1901. 2 letters; 1877-1883., (152)
      - Fiske, Minnie Maddern (Davey), 1865-1932. 5 letters; 1900 [n.d.]., (153)
      - Fitch, Clyde, 1865-1909. 2 letters; [n.d.]., (154)
      - Forbes, James, 1871-. 1 letter; 1914., (155)
      - Ford, James Lauren, 1854-1928. 1 letter; 1919., (156)
      - Foster, Frank E. 8 letters; 1862-1864., (157)
      - Fraser, Daniel. 7 letters; 1875-1876 [n.d.]., (158)
      - Fréchette, Louis Honoré, 1839-1908. 1 letter; 1885., (159)
      - Frederic, Harold, 1856-1898. 3 letters; 1885-1898., (160)
      - Freeman, Mary Eleanor (Wilkins), 1862-1930. 1 letter; 1900., (161)
      - French, Alice, 1850-1934. 2 letters; 1887-1888., (162)
      - Fuller, George, 1822-1884. 1 letter; 1883., (163)
      - Fuller, Henry Blake, 1857-1929. 12 letters; 1893-1919 [n.d.]., (164)
      - Furness, Horace Howard, 1833-1912. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (165)
      - Furnivall, Frederick James, 1825-1910. 4 letters; 1877-1903., (166)
        Gabrilowitsch, Clara (Clemens). See Clemens, Clara.
      - Gardener, Helen Hamilton (Chenoweth) 1858-1925. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (167)
      - Garfield, James Abram, pres. U.S., 1831-1881. 2 letters; 1871-1873., (168)
      - Garfield, Lucretia (Rudolph) 1832-1918. 1 letter; 1881., (169)
      - Garland, Hamlin, 1860-1940. 5 letters; 1890 [n.d.]., (170)
      - Garrison, Francis Jackson, 1848-1916. 5 letters; 1881-1915., (171)
      - George, Henry, 1839-1897. 1 letter; 1893., (172)
      - Gibson, Charles Dana, 1867-1944. 1 letter; 1891., (173)
      - Gilder, Jeannette Leonard, 1849-1916. 3 letters; 1881-1891., (174)
      - Gilder, Richard Watson, 1844-1909. 72 letters; 1874-1909 [n.d.]., (175)
        No. 72 is incomplete copy of a letter from Roswell Smith, with a note from R.W. Gilder to W.D. Howells.
      - Gill, Wilfred Austin. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (176)
      - Gillette, William, 1853-1937. 3 letters; 1881-1916., (177)
      - Gilman, Charlotte (Perkins) Stetson, 1860-1935. 5 letters; 1890-1919., (178)
        Letter of 1897 April 6 is to Elinor Mead Howells.
      - Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1831-1908. 7 letters; 1882-1884 [n.d.]., (179)
      - Gilson, Roy Rolfe, 1875-1933. 1 letter; 1905., (180)
      - Gladden, Washington, 1836-1918. 1 letter; 1893., (181)
      - Goschen, George Joachim Goschen, viscount, 1831-1907. 1 letter; 1904., (182)
      - Gosse, Sir Edmund, 1849-1928. 35 letters; 1882-1911., (183)
        Nos. 4, 20, 23-25, 27, 28 published in Evan Charteris, The life and letters of Sir Edmund Gosse.
      - Graham, James Lorimer, 1835-1876. 2 letters; 1862-1863., (184)
      - Graham, Margaret (Collier) 1850-1910. 1 letter; 1899., (185)
      - Grand, Sarah, pseud., 1855-1943. 1 letter; 1912., (186)
      - Greenslet, Ferris, 1875-1959. 2 letters; 1915., (187)
        Greenwood, Grace, pseud. See Lippincott, Sara Jane (Clarke) 1823-1904.
        Gréville, Henry, pseud. See Durand, Alice Marie Céleste (Fleury) 1842-1902.
      - Grey, William, 9th earl of Stamford, 1850-1910. 2 letters; 1890-1891., (188)
      - Guernsey, Alfred Hudson, 1825-1902. 1 letter; 1864., (189)
      - Guiney, Louise Imogen, 1861-1920. 1 letter; 1888., (190)
      - Guthrie, Thomas Anstey, 1856-1934. 1 letter; 1900., (191)